And the Jewish belief of Jesus, you
know, is just not something that uh
any Christian is or should be willing to
entertain. He said, "I would like to
invite you into the embrace of Islam."
>> You've been in the CIA.
You've seen things other people probably
couldn't imagine realistically. And
you've been in jail for doing something
righteous, right?
How did the faith help you through these
struggles?
>> Oh, the faith got me through.
Um one of the things that I haven't
talked about very much, just because
nobody's asked me,
was
the role of Orthodoxy in my life in
prison.
So,
I'm going to just come right out with
it. I I copped an attitude in prison.
I figured, "You know what? I did
something that was right. I'm being
punished for political reasons. I'm not
apologizing to anybody." So, I had an
attitude. I'm the first one to admit it.
I um
I did not fit in in the library. The
guards there hated me and hated my
attitude and told me to get out and
never never come back.
Which was great, cuz it was all full of
pedophiles anyway.
So, I went down to the chapel. And I
told the chaplain I'd really like to
work in the chapel. You have to have a
job in prison. You have to, even if it's
kind of a no-show job or no-work job,
you have to have something.
So, uh
the chaplain liked me
and hired me. I was the only Orthodox uh
Christian in the chapel. There was only
one other Orthodox Christian in the uh
prison. He was a Ukrainian American, but
he was a pedophile. So, I didn't have
anything to do with him.
When I got to the chapel,
my job was to um just give out books or
videos for any prisoner that would come
to the window and say, "Hey, can I take
such and such a book? Or can I watch
this video?"
They had their own video library there.
And I said to the chaplain,
"Why no Orthodox books?
You got a whole wall for the Catholics,
a whole wall for the Protestants, a
whole wall for the Mormons and the
Muslims and the Jews and the Native
Americans and the Wiccans and this one
and that one, religions I never even
heard of.
And he said, "We either never had an
Orthodox or never had an Orthodox who
cared."
Well, um
Metropolitan Savas of Pittsburgh has
always been a big supporter of mine.
And he would come to the prison to
visit, just like a normal visitor, but
he would come with his big hat and his
staff and everything. It was great.
So, he asked me, um "What can What can I
do to help Man, excuse me.
What can I do to help you?" And I said,
"Well, to tell you the truth, Your
Eminence, there's really nothing anybody
can do to help me, but what would be
helpful to
people after me
is if you could uh get some books on
Orthodoxy and send them in and I'll make
sure that they become part of the
library."
So, he sent Father Michael Callos of
suburban Pittsburgh from a Greek
Orthodox church there.
Father Michael used to come all the time
to see me. He's a great guy. He's a uh
uh friend of my sister's. And um
these books just started arriving.
And then there was a Russian Orthodox
priest from Altoona, Pennsylvania who
used to come
not as often as the other two, but he
would come
regularly. And he would always bring
books.
And so, by the time I left, we had a
full-fledged Orthodox library at the
prison. I know that's a small point, but
it's something that I'm proud of. And
another thing, too,
Orthodox Christian Prison Ministries,
which you can find on Facebook and
Twitter and, you know, Instagram and all
that stuff. They were incredibly
generous. Um
I don't even know. I I mean, one of my
priest friends must have told them about
me because as soon as I arrived,
they started sending me paper icons and,
you know, flyers, sermons, holy days,
stuff like that. It was incredibly
helpful.
So, it all kind of came together.
>> Is it tough to follow the fast and the
feast in prison?
>> It's impossible.
>> Yeah, I would assume so.
>> Unless you have outside money
allowing you to buy things in the in the
commissary. One thing I did, and I wish
it had been my idea cuz it was a great
idea, I but I didn't think of it.
There was an Iraqi Kurdish prisoner that
I was friendly with.
Um and uh
he was kind of wandering around the
prison yard one day, and it was just as
Lent was starting.
And I said, "What are you doing?"
And he said, "I'm picking
uh dandelion leaves." And I said,
"Horta, it never even occurred to me."
So, I said, "Do you mind if I pick some,
too? I don't want to take your
dandelions. I'll go to the other side of
the of the yard." He said, "No, no, no."
He said, "Pick. Nobody knows what they
are around here. Pick whatever you
want."
So, I picked a huge bag of of wild uh
dandelions
and then went to the commissary and got
olive oil. And to tell you the truth,
that kind of got me through Lent.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you did fully follow the feast
almost? Like you
>> Not fully. There were some days they
wouldn't let you out cuz it's, you know,
raining all day.
Or um
there were some days where
there was just nothing Lenten.
And you either had to violate it or or
go uh go hungry.
So, I tried to buy
things in the commissary as best I
could.
Um they sell tuna in bags, like foil
bags. So, I went through a lot of tuna.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. But then it's, you know, rice with
no stock or, you know, whatever you can
find.
>> So, I have this personal question that's
I I've been sitting on for months and
months and months. I need to ask this.
So, you talk a lot about the Abu
Zubaydah thing, right? You talked about
debating Christianity and Islam with
him.
What kind of things were you debating
about with him?
>> You know, it was more that we were
agreeing than debating.
>> Mhm.
Um
of course the Muslims believe that
Christ was not just a prophet, but he
was
one of the greatest prophets. Muhammad
of course being the greatest.
Jesus is right up there like almost as
an equal, almost. They don't believe
that he was crucified.
They have this kind of odd belief that
it was somebody who looked like Jesus
who was crucified and that Jesus
escaped.
So we kind of debated that and he said,
you know, we both acknowledge that that
the Jews were wrong at the time of of
Christ. And I said, yes, of course we
both acknowledge. And the and the Jewish
belief of Jesus, you know, in burning
and excrement in hell is just not
something that uh
any Christian
is or should be willing to entertain.
And um
so it at least gave us something on
which we could agree and carry on a
civilized conversation as two adults.
And he wasn't the only one who was like
that. Um the very first prisoner I
captured was was a Jordanian.
It was funny. I I wish every prisoner
had been like him.
Because they brought him in the
Pakistanis brought him into this
interrogation room that we had and they
chained him to an eye bolt in the table.
And I was thinking in advance, should I
be the good cop? Should I be the bad
cop? Should I be like mean to him? And
then I thought, I don't know what I'm
doing. I'm just going to sit and have a
conversation with this guy.
So I said, what's your name? And boom,
he told me his name.
Like the tribal name and the whole
thing.
When were you born? And he told me and
you know, it sounded right. And I said,
uh what were you doing in Afghanistan?
And he said, well, I went to Afghanistan
3 years ago to volunteer to build an
orphanage. I worked at an orphanage in
Jordan and he went into this long story.
Like with every prisoner I laid out a
map of the Afghan-Pakistan border area
and I told him, "Tell me exactly how you
got from Afghanistan to Pakistan." We
knew how they all got through the pass,
but he told me the truth.
And every question that I asked him, he
told me the truth.
So,
I said, "Okay. Well,
thank you."
And uh he said, "Uh what's going to
happen to me?" And I said, "To tell you
the truth, I'm not sure.
You're Jordanian. We're very close to
the Jordanians. We'll probably just send
you back to Jordan, and then you can
just deal with your own government." We
hadn't yet opened Guantanamo.
And um
he said, "Now, may I ask you a
question?"
And I said, "Oh,
sure."
He said, "I would like to invite you
into the embrace of Islam, and I would
like to be your godfather."
>> Wow.
>> And I said, "Well, thank you. I have a
faith. I'm I'm an Orthodox Christian,
but uh but I appreciate you thinking
about me. Thank you for that." And he
said, "Well, good luck to you." I said,
"No, good luck to you."
And then he kind of We had him chained,
but he put his hand out to shake my
hand, and I thought, "Well, I wish
everybody was was like him." They
weren't,
but Hina Rabani Khar wanted to have this
conversation.
>> Do you think like part of their demeanor
towards you was because they were the
ones locked up in chains?
>> I asked him that.
>> Okay.
>> And I said, "Why would you Why would you
answer all my questions truthfully? I
know you were telling the truth."
And he said,
"What good would it do me to lie?
I'm your prisoner.
Lying help me in any way."
And I said, "True enough. I appreciate
it."
>> Wow.
So,
do you have any other stories about kind
of dealing with
uh specifically like Muslims during your
time in CIA, and how you kind of debated
Christianity? Like what arguments do you
usually use when you're debating with
the
the terrorist, or even if it's some
other person?
>> The terrorists aside, I never really did
any
debates
>> Okay.
>> uh specifically. They were
conversations.
Um in Bahrain, Bahrain to me was one of
the most interesting because there were
churches in Bahrain, just no Orthodox
churches. Well, there was one Malayalam
Orthodox, but we're not in communion
with the Malayalam Orthodox Eastern
>> Is that the Indian
>> The Indian South Indian Orthodox Church
of uh St. Thomas. So, um I went there
once uh with my wife. Our son was 16
months old. And we we came out. And my
wife goes, "What do you think?" And men
were on one side, women were veiled, and
on the other side.
She says, "What do you think?" And I
said, "Honestly, I was waiting for them
to sacrifice a chicken or something. I
don't know what the heck was going on in
there."
And everybody like spent half the
liturgy just turned and looked at me
looking at me like, "Who's this white
guy?" You know, in our church. So, it
was weird.
So, we ended up going on Sundays to the
um to the Anglican Cathedral just cuz it
was closer.
There was a Catholic church that we
never went to.
I I wasn't I
had no interest in going to the Catholic
church. Uh but the Anglicans were very,
very warm and friendly. After I'd been
there for a year,
and I was friends with all the Greeks
and all the Cypriots on the island.
They're all very successful bankers,
investment advisors, construction big
shots. And then the honorary Greek
uh consul
uh was a Greek-American woman from right
here in um in suburban Washington.
So, we were
constantly inviting
the whole group to lunch and dinner and
parties and stuff like that. So, she
calls me one day and she said, "Hey, the
the Archbishop of Cyprus wants to come."
I said, "Hey, that's great."
They used to joke and they even joked to
the Emir, His Highness the Emir, that
I loved Bahrain so much and I I so many
visitors come to Bahrain that he should
name me Minister of Tourism.
>> Wow.
>> So, I said I said if he's going to be
here for more than a minute, I'd love to
show him the island, take him to the
museums and
and she said we have a whole plan
uh worked out and he's going to come
here to ask for a plot of land so we can
build a church. I was like, "Oh my god."
Well, the Emir liked me a lot. I think
he especially liked my wife. The Emir
had a um
a beach house, one of his many palaces.
It was on the beach and on weekends
uh Westerners or more specifically
people from a culture that doesn't stare
>> Okay.
>> could go to the beach and wear bathing
suits and go swimming. So, my wife could
wear a bikini and we would take our son
and we go to the beach. Well, if the
Emir were there for the weekend and he
usually was,
um he would send one of his lackeys over
to us and invite my wife for tea and
then an hour later the lackey would come
back and say uh His Highness would like
to see you now.
So, he took a liking to me.
And he knew that I loved Bahrain.
The Archbishop comes and it's this big
deal that all of the Orthodox on the
island and it had to be like 40 of us
uh go to the main palace to meet with
His Highness.
And uh and the two of them are sitting
up at the front of the diwan and the
rest of us are sitting like facing them.
And then they finish their meeting and
they're whispering to one another. They
finish the meeting and they stand up so
we all stand up to follow them out and
he points at me and he goes like this.
So,
I went and I said, "Yes, Your Highness."
And he says,
"I like your Imam."
>> [laughter]
>> And I said, "I think he likes you, too."
So, we all walked out
and then
we got in the cars and went to the home
of um this big property developer who
was Cypriot. And when we got there, the
archbishop said, "He gave us the land."
And he said we can start construction on
a church immediately.
>> Beautiful.
>> And so now there's an Orthodox church in
Bahrain.
>> And who's the bishop that it's under?
>> Uh it's it's under the the uh
Cypriot archdiocese.
>> Okay, wow. Interesting. Church of
Cyprus.
>> Very interesting.
>> Yeah.